# **Thomas Harrop**

I am a post-doctoral researcher with a background in bioinformatics, genetics and molecular biology and an interest in basic and applied research relating to agriculture.

I have advanced programming skills in R, Python and shell scripting. I am experienced working in molecular, plant, animal and medical laboratories and installing, maintaining and using computers running Unix, Linux and MacOS.

#### Personal information

Date of birth 25 December 1982

Nationalities Australian and British

Languages English (native), German (TELC Level B2) and French (TELC Level B1)

## **Education**

**2006–2012** Doctor of Philosophy, Department of Genetics, the University of

Melbourne, Parkville, Australia.

Thesis: The functions of cytochrome P450s in Drosophila.

During my Ph.D. I used classical genetics and modern molecular biology, including transgenic manipulation of gene expression and comparative studies of gene function, to investigate the functions of

cytochrome P450 genes in the Drosophila genus.

2002–2005 Bachelor of Science with Honours (first class), the University of

Melbourne, Parkville, Australia.

# **Experience**

**2014–Present** Post-doctoral researcher, UMR DIADE, Institut de Recherche pour le

Développement (IRD), Montpellier, France.

In my current project I am working on the development of inflorescence

architecture in rice, which is related to grain yield potential. We used a precise laser microdissection and RNA sequencing approach to characterise molecular events that occur during the transitions between meristem types in the developing inflorescence. We are

now applying these results to study the effects of selection on gene expression during the parallel domestications of African and Asian rice. Whilst working on this project I have expanded my skills in bioinformatic analysis and statistics and gained a knowledge of plant biology and agronomy.

**2013–2014** Post-doctoral researcher, Department of Plant Breeding and

Genetics, Max Planck Institute for Plant Breeding Research, Cologne,

Germany.

At the Max Planck Insitute I worked on a project to compare the transcriptional response of several different land plants to UV-B exposure, which acts as an environmental signal. This position provided hands-on experience with plant biology and a foundation to apply my programming and bioinformatic skills.

#### **Professional positions**

**2004–2007** Medical scientist, Network Pathology, the Austin Hospital, Heidelberg,

Australia.

**2001–2004** Laboratory assistant, Network Pathology, the Austin Hospital,

Heidelberg, Australia.

**Teaching** 

2007–2011 3<sup>rd</sup> Year Genetics, Department of Genetics, The University of

Melbourne, Parkville, Australia.

**2006–2009 High School Biology**, Department of Genetics, The University of

Melbourne, Parkville, Australia.

2006–2008 High School Biology, Gene Technology Access Centre, The University

High School, Parkville, Australia.

**2005–2008 1**<sup>st</sup> **Year Genetics**, The University of Melbourne, Parkville, Australia.

Students co-supervised

**Swarit Jaisal** Master of Science, Life Science Informatics, Universität Bonn,

Germany.

**Axel Verdier** Master of Science, Sciences et Technologies de l'Information et de la

Communication pour la Santé, Université de Montpellier, France.

### **Publications**

#### Peer-reviewed journals

- Harrop, T.W.R.<sup>§</sup>, Ud Din, I.<sup>§</sup>, Gregis, V., Osnato, M., Jouannic, S., Adam, H. and Kater, M. (2016). Gene expression profiling of reproductive meristem types in early rice inflorescences by laser microdissection. The Plant Journal (accepted manuscript). doi:10.1111/tpj.13147.
- **Harrop**, **T.W.R.**<sup>§</sup>, Pearce, S.L.<sup>§</sup>, Daborn, P.J. and Batterham, P. (2014). Whole-genome expression analysis in the third instar larval midgut of *Drosophila melanogaster*. G3 (Bethesda) 4, 2197–2205. <u>doi:10.1534/g3.114.013870</u>.
- Harrop, T.W.R., Sztal, T., Lumb, C., Good, R.T., Daborn, P.J., Batterham, P. and Chung, H. (2014). Evolutionary changes in gene expression, coding sequence and copy-number at the *Cyp6g1* locus contribute to resistance to multiple insecticides in Drosophila. Plos One 9, e84879. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0084879.
- Daborn, P.J., Lumb, C., **Harrop, T.W.R.**, Blasetti, A., Pasricha, S., Morin, S., Mitchell, S.N., Donnelly, M.J., Müller, P. and Batterham, P., (2012). Using *Drosophila melanogaster* to validate metabolism-based insecticide resistance from insect pests. Insect Biochemistry and Molecular Biology 42, 918–924. doi:10.1016/j.ibmb.2012.09.003.

#### **Selected conference presentations**

- **Harrop, T.W.R.**, Gregis, V., Ud Din, I., Kater, M., Jouannic, S. and Adam, H. *Molecular mechanisms* underlying the phenotypic convergence of inflorescence architecture in domesticated rice species. Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution annual meeting, 2015, Vienna, Austria
- **Harrop, T.W.R.**, Ud Din, I., Gregis, V., Osnato, M., Jouannic, S., Adam, H. and Kater, M. *Transcriptomic analysis of early developmental stages of the rice panicle*. Workshop in Molecular Mechanisms Controlling Flowering, 2015, Aiguablava, Spain.
- **Harrop, T.W.R.**, Batterham, P. and Daborn, P.J. RNA interference of the Cytochrome P450 redox partners Cpr and dare uncovers novel P450 functions in Drosophila melanogaster. The 50th Annual Drosophila Research Conference, 2009, Chicago, USA.

### Other information

**Research interests** Plant and insect research related to **agronomy**, tools and techniques in

bioinformatics and evolutionary and comparative biology.

**Technical experience** Aside from daily use of R, Python and bash scripts, I also use

Markdown regularly and have experience with Perl, LaTeX, html and css. I use git and GitHub for version control and strive to follow the principles of reproducible research when coding. I have used several different workload managers for cluster computing

<sup>§</sup> Equal contribution

including SGE and and LSF, and I maintain an installation of SLURM on my personal workstation.

I have experience in molecular biology techniques such as quantitative real-time PCR, cloning, nucleic acid extraction and cDNA library preparation, as well as classical genetic approaches with live organisms, such as transformation, crosses, microdissection and bioassays.

About me

Outside work I have a range of interests including building and riding bicycles, social football and basketball, cooking, programming and technology.

**Awards** 

2006–2009, Australian Postgraduate Award

<u>twharrop@gmail.com</u> · <u>GitHub</u> · <u>stackoverflow</u> Castelnau-le-Lez, Hérault, FRANCE